Yassine Laguel's Resume

CONTACT INFORMATION

Laboratoire Jean Alexandre Dieudonné

Université Côte d'Azur

Phone: +33-745030188

28 avenue Valrose,

Mail: yassine.laguel@univ-cotedazur.fr
https://yassine-laguel.github.io

Nice, 06108, France

RESEARCH INTERESTS My interests center around optimization under uncertainty and its applications to stochastic programming and machine learning. A common thread in my research is the design and analysis of numerical algorithms to address risk in data-driven applications. I draw and extend ideas and tools from convex optimization, probability theory and numerical analysis while keeping an *operational* approach, with a balance between theoretical and practical contributions.

ACADEMIC POSITIONS

Université Côte d'Azur,

Sep 2023 - Present

Associate Professor.

Nice, France.

Rutgers University,

Jan 2022 - June 2023

Postdoctoral Associate at the Department of Management Sciences and Information Systems (MSIS), hosted by Prof. Mert Gürbüzbalaban.

New Brunswick, USA.

Princeton University,

Fall 2022

Departmental Guest at the Center for Statistics and Machine Learning (CSML).

Princeton, USA.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Optimization and Machine Learning,

Oct 2018 - Nov 2021

Supervised by Jérôme Malick, Université Grenoble Alpes, Grenoble, France.

B.S., M.S. in Computer Sciences and Applied Mathematics

Sep 2015 - Sep 2018

Diplôme d'ingénieur from ENSIMAG, Grenoble France.

B.S., M.S. in Mathematics

Sep 2015 - Sep 2018

Master major in statistics, Université Grenoble Alpes, Grenoble, France. Degrees pursued in parallel to my diplôme d'ingénieur.

JOURNAL PAPERS

- [1] **Yassine Laguel**, Mert Gürbüzbalaban, Necdet Serhat Aybat. High probability and riskaverse guarantees for stochastic saddle point problems. 2023. Preprint. https://yassine-laguel.github.io/files/risk-averse-minimax.pdf
- [2] **Yassine Laguel**, Wim Van Ackooij, Jérôme Malick. Chance constrained problems: a bilevel convex optimization perspective. 2023. Preprint. https://yassine-laguel.github.io/files/taco-paper.pdf
- [3] Yu-Guan Hsieh, **Yassine Laguel**, Franck Iutzeler, Jérôme Malick. Push–pull with device sampling. *IEEE Transactions in Automatic Control*. 2023. https://yassine-laguel.github.io/files/ppds-paper.pdf
- [4] **Yassine Laguel**, Krishna Pillutla, Jérôme Malick, Zaid Harchaoui. Federated learning with heterogeneous data: a superquantile optimization approach. *Machine Learning Journal*. 2023. https://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.09429.pdf
- [5] Yassine Laguel. Risk-averse optimization: models, algorithms, and applications in machine learning. *Ph.D. Dissertation*. 2022. https://yassine-laguel.github.io/files/phd_thesis.pdf

- [6] **Yassine Laguel**, Jérôme Malick, Zaid Harchaoui. Superquantile-based learning: a direct approach using gradient-based optimization. *Journal of Signal Processing Systems*. No. 94, pages 161–177. 2022. https://yassine-laguel.github.io/files/2021_jsps.pdf
- [7] Yassine Laguel, Wim Van Ackooij, Jérôme Malick, Guilherme Matiussi Ramalho. On the convexity of level-sets of probability functions. *Journal of Convex Analysis*. No. 29.2, pages 411-442. 2022. https://yassine-laguel.github.io/files/transconcavity-paper.pdf
- [8] Yassine Laguel, Krishna Pillutla, Jérôme Malick, Zaid Harchaoui. Superquantiles at work: machine learning applications and efficient (sub)gradient computation. Set-Valued and Variational Analysis. No. 29, pages 967–996. 2022. https://yassine-laguel. github.io/files/svaa-paper.pdf.
- [9] Gilles Bareilles, Yassine Laguel, Dmitry Grishchenko, Franck Iutzeler, Jerome Malick. Randomized progressive hedging methods for multi-stage stochastic programming. *Annals of Operations Research*. No. 295, pages 535–560. 2020. https://arxiv.org/abs/2009.12186

CONFERENCE PAPERS

- [10] Yassine Laguel, Krishna Pillutla, Jérôme Malick, Zaid Harchaoui. Tackling Distribution Shifts in Federated Learning with Superquantile Aggregation. NeurIPS 2022 Workshop on Distribution Shifts: Connecting Methods and Applications. Spotlight paper. 2022.
- [11] **Yassine Laguel**, Krishna Pillutla, Jérôme Malick, Zaid Harchaoui. Differentially Private Federated Quantiles with the Distributed Discrete Gaussian Mechanism. *International Workshop on Federated Learning: Recent Advances and New Challenges*. 2022.
- [12] Yassine Laguel, Krishna Pillutla, Jérôme Malick, Zaid Harchaoui. Device heterogeneity in federated learning: a superquantile approach. Proceedings of the 55th Annual Conference on Information Sciences and Systems (CISS 2021). https://arxiv.org/abs/2002. 11223
- [13] Yassine Laguel, Jérôme Malick, Zaid Harchaoui. First order optimization for superquantile-based supervised learning. Proceedings of the Machine Learning and Signal Processing Conference (MLSP 2020) Best Student Paper Award. https://arxiv.org/abs/2009. 14575

SOFTWARE TACO 2022

Python toolbox for chance constrained optimization. Yassine Laguel, Wim Van Ackooij, Jérôme Malick. https://yassine-laguel.github.io/taco/.

SPOR 2020

Python toolbox for superquantile minimization. Yassine Laguel, Jérôme Malick, Zaid Harchaoui. https://yassine-laguel.github.io/spqr/.

RandomizedProgressiveHedging.jl

2019

Julia toolbox for solving multistage stochastic problems by randomized versions of the progressive hedging algorithm. Gilles Bareilles, Yassine Laguel, Dmitry Grishchenko, Franck Iutzeler, Jerome Malick. https://yassine-laguel.github.io/RandomizedProgressiveHedging.jl/stable.

INVITED TALKS

On the acceleration/robustness trade-off for stochastic min-max problems

• Telecom Paris

Robustness for Models and Algorithms in Machine Learning *Talk.* Saclay, France.

• Laboratoire Jean Alexandre Dieudonné

2023

Robustness for Models and Algorithms in Machine Learning	
 Talk. Nice, France. Institut Montpelliérain Alexander Grothendieck Robustness for Models and Algorithms in Machine Learning Talk. Montpellier, France. 	2022
INFORMS annual meeting A robust perspective on acceleration for saddle point problems Talk. Indianapolis, USA.	2022
• International conference on continuous optimization (ICCOPT) New perspectives on robustness via the Conditional Value at Risk. Talk. Lehigh, USA.	2022
Handling statistical heterogeneity in federated learning	
Magnet Seminar The seminar is	2022
Federated learning with heterogeneous data: a superquantile optimization approach <i>Talk</i> . Inria Lille, France.	n.
University of Washington Machine Learning Seminar	2022
Convex risk measures: models, algorithms and applications in federated learning.	
Talk. Seattle, USA. • Thoth Seminar	2022
Convex risk measures: models, algorithms and applications in federated learning.	
Talk. Inria Grenoble, France.	2021
 Journées des Statistiques Risk-sensitive learning for heterogeneous frameworks. 	2021
Talk. Nice, France.	
Workshop on Communication Efficient Distributed Optimization	2021
Device heterogeneity in federated learning: a superquantile approach. <i>Poster</i> Online workshop.	
Federated Learning One World Seminar	2020
Device heterogeneity in federated learning: a superquantile approach. <i>Talk</i> . Online Seminar.	
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=W-oNzU04Y8I	
Optimization for Machine Learning Conference	2020
Handling device heterogeneity in federated learning.	
Poster. Marseille, France.	
PhD. Defense Pick everse entimization, models, electrithms, and applications in machine learning.	2021
Risk-averse optimization: models, algorithms, and applications in machine learning. <i>Talk</i> . Grenoble, France.	
Hidden convexity in probabilistic programming	
ANSI Seminar	2021
On hidden convexity in chance constrained problems.	
Talk. Los Alamos, USA. • SMAI-MODE Conference	2020
A DC approach for chance constraints.	
Talk. Saclay, France.	
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KB3sV-trEy4&list • International conference on continuous optimization (ICCOPT)	2019
On the interplay between generalized concavity and chance constraints.	2017
Talk. Berlin, Germany.	
Efficient oracles for distributionally robust optimization	
IFDS Workshop on Distributional Robustness in Data Science SPOR A Troubey for Supergraphtile based Learning.	2022
SPQR : A Toolbox for Superquantile-based Learning <i>Talk</i> . Seattle, USA.	

• Machine Learning and Signal Processing Conference (MLSP) 2020 First-order optimization for superquantile-based supervised learning. Best student Paper Award. Talk. Espoo, Finland. https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JRWvWxOxRiQ ROADEF 2020 Practical minimization of CVar-based risk functions. *Talk.* Montpellier, France. • International conference on stochastic programming (ICSP) 2019 1^{st} -order methods for minimization of superquantile-based risk measures. Talk. Trondheim, Norway. Instructor • Fundamentals of analysis and algebra. 50h. Grenoble INP. Undergraduate Course. Grenoble, France. • Fundamentals of analysis and algebra. 50h. Unversité Grenoble Alpes. Undergraduate Course. Grenoble, France. • Introduction to R. 2x30h. Université Grenoble Alpes. Undergraduate Course. Grenoble, France. • Introduction to Python. 2x30h. Université Grenoble Alpes. Graduate Course. Grenoble, France. • Convex and distributed optimization. 18h. Université Grenoble Alpes. Graduate Course. Grenoble, France. • Numerical optimization. 25h. ENSIMAG. Graduate Course. Grenoble, France. **Guest Lecturer** • Distributionally robust machine learning. 4h.

Distributionally robust machine learning.
 University of Washington. *Graduate Course*. Seattle, USA.

 Introduction to federated learning.
 ENSIMAG. *Graduate Course*. Grenoble, France.

PROFESSIONAL SERVICE

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Committee Service

- Founder and Organizer of the Optim & ML Seminar at Rutgers University, since March 2022.
- Founder and Organizer of GORGeous (Grenoble Optimization Reading Group), at the Université Grenoble Alpes, from Sep. 2019 to Oct. 2021.
 https://sites.google.com/view/gorgeous-optim/
- Jury member for the International Tournament of Young Mathematicians (ITYM). Iasi, Romania. 2013.

Referee Service

- Journal of Machine Learning Research (JMLR)
- Mathematics of Operations Research
- EURO Journal on Computational Optimization
- Automatica
- Optimization
- *Journal of Optimization Theory and Applications (JOTA)*

Conference Service

- Program Committee: 51st International Conference on Parallel Processing (ICPP 2022).
- Organizer of the session *First-order methods for min-max problems* at ICCOPT 2022.
- Organizer of the session First-order methods for minimax problems at INFORMS 2022.

PROFESSIONAL **Research Internships** EXPERIENCE • University of Washington, Seattle, USA. 2018 Initiated the series of works [6, 8, 10, 11]. • EDF R&D, Saclay, France. 2017. Led to the publication of the journal paper [7]. • WeSave, Financial Startup in Paris, France. 2016 Worked on the establishment of quantitative criterion based on random correlations matrices to predict crises. **Consulting Activity** 2016 • Conception and development of a transport management software for an international firm. **Spotlight Paper** 2022 **AWARDS** NeurIPS 2022 Workshop on Distribution Shifts: Connecting Methods and Applications. New Orleans, USA. 2020 **Best Student Paper Award** Machine learning and signal processing conference (MLSP 2020). Espoo, Finland. Finalist of the International Tournament of Young Mathematicians (ITYM) 2012 $Rank: 3^{rd}$. Orsay, France. Winner of the French Tournament of Young Mathematicians (TFJM) 2012 Saclay, France.